<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a godly new story of .xii. men that moyses (by the co[m]maundement of god) sent to spye owt the land of canaan of whiche .xii. onely Iosua and Caleb, wer found faythful messengers.</title>
            <author>Nicolls, Philip.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18576</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104164</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839903</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4364</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4364)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 121:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a godly new story of .xii. men that moyses (by the co[m]maundement of god) sent to spye owt the land of canaan of whiche .xii. onely Iosua and Caleb, wer found faythful messengers.</title>
                  <author>Nicolls, Philip.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>The tenth daye of Maye: anno dominice incarnationis M C XLViii. By William Hill remayning at the signe of the hill in Paules Churche yarde: and be there by him to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprented at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle to the reader" signed: Phillyp Nicolls.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; correct publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>In the imprint, the first "n" in "incarnationis" is printed upside down.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The story of .xii. men.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G F⁴.</note>
                  <note>The "C" in the date has been altered to a "D".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moses (Biblical leader) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible stories, English --  O.T. --  Numbers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Here begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly newe ſtory of .xii. men that moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god) ſent to ſpye owt the land of canaan: of whiche .xii. onely Ioſua and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb, wer found faythful meſſengers.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſalme. Cv.</bibl>
               <p>O that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woulde prays y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of god and the wonders that he doth for the chyldren of men: for he hath broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates of braſſe, and ſmytten the barres of Iron in ſunder. Folyſhemen were plaged for their offences &amp; becauſe of their wickednes.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the reader</head>
            <p>To all the faythfull brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che onely deſyre the glory of god, in our ſauiour and Redemer Ieſus Chryſt: be grace mercy and peace thorow the workyng of hys holy ſpirite. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered al thiges do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne;<note place="margin">Eccle. viii</note> to be but vanitie and vexacione of mynde: Yet ſayeth he ys there a vanyte vppon earth. There be iuſt men vnto whom it happeneth as though they had the workes of the vngodly: agayne theyr be vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyth whom it goeth as though they had the workes of the tyghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Thys me thynke alſe a vayne thynge etc. Thys vexed ſaloinon aboue other thynges and moued hym the rather to ſay: al is but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte, when he ſaw good men rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded wyth euel and the wycked flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe and haue proſperyte. he ſawe
<pb facs="tcp:4364:3"/>the Good &amp; the badde proſpere alyke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>creſe their ryches &amp; poſſeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; to be had i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuerenc: he ſaw the wycked decaye &amp; peryſhe, and lykewyſe, it happened to the innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Vnmeate it ſemeth to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good reſon, that a ſoore laborynge man ſhould lack hys meate, and an idle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſleape with a ful belly. But what ſhal we ſaye, lyke as it was in ſalomons dayes: ſo alſo now is it moſt ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that many tymes a man ſhall ſeke hys brothers wealth and ſhew him a greate benefite: &amp; finde hys diſpleaſure and haue his euell wyl that is, for his well doynge ſhalbe rewarded with euel, and yet ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bler haue greate beneuolence &amp; fauoure. Oftentimes it cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nceth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſtly ſtudyeth to profyt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men welth: hath lytell thank for hys labour and is deſpiſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: and he whoſe dylygence may be beſt ſpared, moſt avau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth hym
<pb facs="tcp:4364:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelfe ther by, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to honour. Ryches, poſſeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde happeneth not ſeldome, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked &amp; vngodly, yea they be had in fauour wyth greate men &amp; wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owte any deſeruynge be brought to great dignyte. Peuury, ſcarſite, trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble &amp; aduerſyte, be ſayed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous which feareth god, &amp; his good wyſdom bryngeth him diſpyt. This is wel knowen to ſuch as ſeke wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in chryſte whome fortune alwaye fauoureth not, and haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perymented the aſſaultes of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye. He that reapeth the corne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce eateth non of the bred. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> treadeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyne preſſe drynketh not alway of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine. The labour &amp; trauel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome men take of pure good wyl &amp; alſo effectuous, hath not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor fauour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> concylyateth withowte payne yea &amp; at laſt vnprofitable. But ſhould I now be agreued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wedes grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge
<pb facs="tcp:4364:4"/>amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the corne: Seynge the ldrds ſayeth:<note place="margin">Mat. xiii. pſa. xxvii</note> Let them grow both tyl harueſt? Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my hatred deſtroy ſynne? or doth my ſynne myny ſhe their offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces? fret not thy ſelfe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly (ſaeth a Dauid) be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyous agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euel doers. And why ſo? for they ſhal ſone be cut do wne lyke the graſſe &amp; be wythered as the grene herbe. Put y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thy truſt in the lord &amp; be doyng good, ſo ſhal y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dwell in the land, &amp; it ſhal ſurely feade the .etc. Vnderſtand now ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll reader, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was aboute to wryte thys mater that I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken in hand: I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of bokes ther be abrode in euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hand of dyuers &amp; ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry maters which at very gredely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured of a greate ſorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who ſo laboreth both writig &amp; redig I do very much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. But ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> labors of al ſuch writer tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kefully receau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed trow ye? Ar ther dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſtudy
<pb facs="tcp:4364:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>gratified accordingly? or doth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a purpos &amp; itent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth of chryſtes flocke mought therby be profyted and the people reduced to a chryſten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer ſation and amendment of lyfe: As the auctor intended? Do they reade withe ſuche iudgemente that they receaue the Good and reiecte the badd? No no. The wayghtyer mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, the ſonner paſſed ouer, and the leſſe thanke to the aucthour. But tryflynge matters, fynely Handled are eſtemed. So croked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe is the nature of man and ſo lytell pleaſure haue we in folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the heuenly doctrane of chryſt: And ſo lytell profytte haue they alſo that with ſynglenes of hart la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure therin. But what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſhould the wryters therfore leaue wryty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge, becauſe the moſt parte do not wourthyly receaue it? God forbyd: But rather would I wyſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:4364:5"/>whyche neuer wrote before, ſhould alſo ſette them ſelfes to woorke be ſtowinge the talent that god hath lent them to the moſt aduauntage, And ſeinge it is not lauful for any man (as yet) to preache in an open audyence, on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es he be or hath byne an Apoſtata: (an Apoſtle I ſhould ſay) I purpoſe by the grace of god and the helpynge of hys holy ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, to doo that lyeth in me, to ſpye out the lande of Canaan and to brynge ſuch tydynges as the Lord ſhall open vnto me, in wrytynge, by meanes wherof his people may know theyr Lord the better and at laſt be partakers of that pleſaunt land flowinge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> milke and hony. Now for as much as by all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hods &amp; tokens we approch neare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> borders of thys promyſed land, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is come into the harte of our moiſes which willeth me of euery ſorte to go ſpie
<pb facs="tcp:4364:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre &amp; to bring tidines what maner of contre it is that al his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple myght enter I thought it very good and profytable to publyſhe the ſtorye of theſe .xii. meſſengers written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke of Numeri y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xiii. &amp; .xiiii. cha. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we being admoniſhed by their exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple mai the better know how to behaue owr ſelues in owr iourney, euery man in hys callyng ſpecially ſuch as are purpoſly ſent. Lyft vp your harts therfor brethren vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord beſechyng hi of hys mer cyful goodnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil woucheſafe to gouerne my hart &amp; al others tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uialinge thys heuenly lande &amp; that thorow fayth in his promyſes (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the example of Ioſua &amp; Caleb) we may be found faythful &amp; true meſſengers bryngyng wyth vs the frute of the ſame land &amp; auoidig y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfaithfulnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which brought an euel report vp po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land &amp; cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to ſine we
<pb facs="tcp:4364:6"/>may comfort them ſo, wyth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a glad harte &amp; ſurs hope, of a conſtant fayth we may altogether enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly taberna cle, which chriſt hath prepared for hys electe. Amen</p>
            <closer>Spiritus vbi vult ſpirat <signed>.P.N. .Phillyp Nycolls</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The ſtory</head>
            <p>It ſhal not nede to wryte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hole ſtori word for word i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebut to refer the (gentle reder (to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bok of nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre the .xiii. &amp; .xiiii. Chapters: theffect where of ys thys. After that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell were gone oute of Egypte and had bin a great whyle in the wyldernes:<note place="margin">Num. xiii</note> and nowdrawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng nygh the lande of Canaan, the lord ſpake vnto Moyſes and ſaied ſend furth men to ſpy out the land of. Canaan, whych I wyll geue vn to the chyldren of Iſraell of euery trybe of their fathers, a man, and let them be ſuche as are captaynes amonge them. etc. Moyſes dyd ſo choſe oute of euerye trybe a man &amp; ſente the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furth and bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vieu y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land and ſee what maner of cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre yt was, and what maner of people they were that dwelte in yt, &amp; alſo to brynge ſome of the frute of the land wyth them. Thei went &amp; after
<pb facs="tcp:4364:7"/>.xl. dayes they returned and came to Moyſes and Aaron and the hole Congregacyon, and declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they had townde a goodly Contre flowinge with milke, &amp; hony &amp; they had broughte of the frute of the lande, A Cluſter of Grapes, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megranetes, &amp; fygges. But ther be ſtronge people dwellynge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land and grate and myghtye Cytyes: we are not able to go agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaye they:) for all the men are of greate ſtature: yea we ſaw Gyauntes there alſo, as the Children of Enock, &amp; we ſemed in our ſyght as the greſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, &amp; ſo dyd we in their ſyghte. At thys report,<note place="margin">Nu. xiii.</note> the Chyldren of Iſrael toke on and cryed and wepte and murmured Agaynſte Moyſes and Aaron, &amp; ſayed: oh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had dyed in Egypt, or that we myght dye yet in thys wylderneſſe. Wherefore bryn geth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord vs into thys land, that our wyues ſhoulde fall thorowe the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſword, &amp; our Chyldren to be a prey. Is yt not better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we goo agayne into Egypte? And they ſayed, one to another: let vs make a Captaine and goo into Egypte agayne.</p>
            <p>But Moyſes &amp; Aaron fel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their faces before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Congregacion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael: and Ioſua the Sonne of Nun and Caleb the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of Iephun (which wer alſo .ii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xii. that had bene to ſpy out the land:) rente theire clothes and ſpake to the hole Congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chyldren of Iſrael and ſayde: the land which we haue walked tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to ſpye yt owte, ys a verye good lande: yff the lorde haue luſte vnto vs, he ſhall brynge vs, into the ſame land &amp; geue yt vs, wiche is a land that floweth wyth milke and hony. But in any wyſe, rebel ye not agaynſt the Lord, and feare not the people of thys land: for we wyl eat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp as bread. Theire defence ys
<pb facs="tcp:4364:8"/>ys departed from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the lorde ys with vs, be not ye affrayed of them. And al the people bad ſtone them with ſtones. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appered the glory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tabernacle of wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vnto all the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. And the Lorde ſayed vnto Moſes: how long ſhal thys people blaſp heme me? And how longe wyll yt be eare they beleue me, for all the tokens that I haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed among them I wyl ſmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peſtilence and deſtroye them, and wil mak of the a greter &amp; a mightier people then thys ys. But Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſayed: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall the Egiptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s heare yt (for with poure haſt thou brought this people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ſo ſhall yt be told to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>habyters of thys lande alſo whyche haue herd that thou o lord arte amonge thys people that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art ſeen from face to face, and that thy clowd ſtande the ouer them, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> goeſt before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cloudy pyller on the day tyme, and in the fyrye piller in the nyght ceaſon. Yf thou ſhouldeſt now ſlea thys people, as one manne, than the heathen that haue hearde ſo good report of thee, ſhould ſay: The lord was not able to bryng the people into the lande that he ſware vnto them, therfore hath he ſlayne them in the wyldernes. So let the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the lorde now be great accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as thou haſt ſpoken and ſayd: the lord ys of long ſufferaunce and of greate mercy, and forgeueth ſyn and treſpaſſe, and leaueth no man inocent, and vyſyteth the myſdedes of the fathers, vpon the cyldren vnto the thyrd and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon. O be gracyous now vnto the ſynne of thys people accordynge to thy great mercy, lyke as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne this people alſo euer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Egi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pte vnto this place. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſaid I haue forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> itas y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſaid, but
<pb facs="tcp:4364:9"/>as truly as I lyue, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be full of my glorye. For of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue ſeene my glory, &amp; my to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, which I dyd in Egypte, &amp; in the wylderneſſe &amp; tempted me now .x. tymes and haue not hearkened vnto my voyce. et c. For I haue heard theyr murmurynges agaynſt me: tell theim therefor, As truly as I lyue (ſayeth the Lorde) I wyll do vnto you, euen as ye haue ſpoken in myn eares. Your carcaſes ſhall lye in thys wylderneſſe: But my ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunte Caleb, becauſe there is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother maner of ſprete in him, and becauſe he hath folowed me: hym wyll I bryng into the land, and Ioſua the ſonne of Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But ye wyth your carcaſſes ſhall lye in thys wylderneſſe: And your chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall beare your myſdeades, fourty yeres, for the .xl. dayes that you were aſpyenge out of the land, a day for a yere, that ye may know
<pb facs="tcp:4364:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>what it is wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> draw my hand. euen I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord haue ſaied it &amp; wil do it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deid vnto al this euel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gtega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue lyft vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſte me: i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys wilderneſſe ſhal they be conſumed, &amp; there ſhal they dye. And their dedes wer plaged before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom moyſes ſent to ſpy owt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land, ſaue Ioſua &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leb. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moyſes had declared this to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, they toke greate ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row, &amp; they roſe early in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyng &amp; went vp to the toppe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and ſayed: Io we are here rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go vpp to the place that the lorde commaunded vs: for we haue ſynned. But Moyſes ſayed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go ye on thys maner beyonde the woorde of the Lorde? Yt ſhalle not proſper with you. Goe not vp (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde is not among vs) hat ye be not ſlayn of your enymyes. But they wer blinded &amp; wold go vp: not withſtanding Moiſes and Aaron
<pb facs="tcp:4364:10"/>nor the arke of couenaunt came not into the hoſt and thre they were ſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yne euery one of the enemyes.</p>
            <p>Here haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> (derely beloued i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt) almoſt the hole matter euen as it is wrytten. Now ſhal it be (in my iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dgement) very profytable to recyte it agayne and applye it to owr tym that it may be prynted the better i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> owr mynde, and that we may both learne by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beware of infidely te &amp; impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we murmur not agaynſt god &amp; neglecte hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; alſo to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of. Caleb and. Ioſua in faith &amp; beleue, doyng all thyng accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord.<note place="margin">Eebre. iii.</note> Thys counſel doth ſaynt Paul ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs ſaige take hede good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of yow an euel hart of vnbeleue to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuiggod but exhort out ſelues daili whil it is called to day leſt ani of you wax hard harted throu y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceatfulnes
<pb facs="tcp:4364:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e etc. Take hed ſay eth he. By thys we may perceaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thorow vnbeleue we departe from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god &amp; for lacke of dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortactyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wax hard harted tho row y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deceatfulns of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue. He that hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder &amp; perceaue wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtat of vnbeleffe &amp; ſpeacilli whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart is once hardned thorow ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not me ruayle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynt Paule ſayeth take hede. For ſuer, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, muſt take hede &amp; feare for he ſhal haue many emmies,<note place="margin">Eccle. ii.</note> the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght goddes ſeruyce (ſayeth ſyrach (&amp; het ſerueth god wel y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feareth to diſpleſe hi now ar all thoſe thinges wrytten for our lernyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mought lerne both by examples &amp; exhortacions to feare god &amp; do his wyl.<note place="margin">Exo. ii. vii. viii xi. x. xiiii.</note> The chyldren of Iſrael, after that the egyptyans be gonne to make ſlaues of then cryed vnto the lord and ſyghed to be dely ueredat, but after the the lordehade
<pb facs="tcp:4364:11"/>wrought many wonders in Egypt for their delyueraunce, and cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea to open &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rome, and pharao with his hooſt drowned: yet al this notwithſtandynge, aſſon as any temptacion aroſe, they forgart altogether &amp;,<note place="margin">Ex. xv xvi xvii. Gene. xvii xxv. xxxv Exo. xiii. Exo. xxxii Nu xxxv. pſal. c. vi.</note> murmured agaynſte the lorde &amp; wyſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they had dyed in Egypt: althoughe the lorde had promiſed their fathers abraa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſaac &amp; Iacob, to multyplye their ſeade, bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; bryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floweth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> milk &amp; hony: yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lord we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pyller of a clowde by day &amp; by nyght i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pyller of fyre. All thys notwithſtandyng (I ſaye) for euery tryfle, they murmured, &amp; gruged, wyſhyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues agayn in egypte: euen diſpyſyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ther god, &amp; made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other goddes, &amp; ſerued the goddes of the nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; went a whoring after ther owne inuencyons: for which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord plaged them often, very ſore. Thes
<pb facs="tcp:4364:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>are examples vnto vs ſayeth ſaynt Paule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould not luſtafter euel thynges,<note place="margin">i. cor. x.</note> as they luſted: nether be ye worſhypers of images, as were ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them, accordynge as it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the people ſate downe to eate &amp; drynke &amp; roſe vp to play,<note place="margin">Exo. xxxii Nn. xxv Nu xxi.</note> nether let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt whordome, as ſom of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted &amp; fel in oneday. xxiii. tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſand: Nether let vs tempte chryſt as ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tempted him &amp; were deſtroyed of ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes:<note place="margin">Num. xi.</note> Neyther mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur ye as ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murmured &amp; were diſtroyed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſtroyer. All theſe happened vnto them for enſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mples (ſayeth ſaynt paule) but they are wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> towarne vs, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde is come: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him that thinketh he ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth take hede leſt he fal. Theſe be ſaynt paules wordes. And I wold wyſhe from my very harte that all men from the hyeſt to the loweſte wolde wey them erneſtly. For they
<pb facs="tcp:4364:12"/>be wrytten for oure learnyng &amp; to thente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we ſhuld take hed frar god &amp; flee ſuch oftences, leſt we pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>voke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde to caſt vs of foreuer. He ſpeaketh eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſeſt among men, ſaynge: let him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinketh he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth take hede leſt he fall. Thys waruyng of ſaint Paul may not be forgotten, take hede therfore breth ten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there be not in any of you an euel hart of vnbelef to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuyug god. Wher withal ſhall ayoung ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his way?<note place="margin">pſal. c. ix.</note> ſayth da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid, he anſwereth him ſelfe &amp; ſayth euen by rulyng him ſelfe after the word of god, but he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goeth beſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord muſt nedes fal tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ugh he thynke hi ſelfe neuer ſo ſure For what is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ory<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">i. cor. i</note> is not wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world foly ſhnes with god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The lord bade Moyſes ſend out.<note place="margin">ſamu. xiii</note> xii, men to ſpye owte the land of canaue. For he wuld geue It to the chyldrenne of Iſraele
<pb facs="tcp:4364:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in poſſeſſyon. Moyſes dyd ſo, and choſe of euery of the, xii tribes, one to go ſpye out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fooles, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the thefe of the trybes. And ther they found a frut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre flowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with mylk &amp; houy. They brought of the grapes, pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granettes, and fygges. All thys was accordinge to the worde of the lorde, and his promys made to the fathers. But as the nature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is alway, to loue him ſelfe to leane to his owne wiſdome, &amp; to put ſome confidence therin and thus forſake fayth: ſo theſe meſſengers ſayed vn to the pople: we cam vnto the land whether ye ſent vs where it flowath withe mylke and hony, and thys is the fruete thereof. Bute then the people are myghtye, theire Cities ſtronge and greate: So that we at not able to matche the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Yea we ſawe gyauntes there alſo, the chyldren or Euocke (ſay they) And we femed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>our ſyght as the greſhoppers and fodyd we in theyr ſyghte lyke wyſe. Now here we ſauhow thei fal away thorow vubelef: for what neded thei haue feared the gia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nts, or any other thynge yf they had beleued god as Abra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fathers did? but thei tok no hed to the word of the lord, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they brought thys euel report vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people theſe wordes beganne to crye and howle ſayeng:<note place="margin">Nu. xiiii.</note> oh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had dyed in the land of Egypte, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we myght dye yet in thys wyldernes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bringeth the lord vs into this land that our wyues ſhuld fal tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſwerd, and our Children be a pray? Is yt not better that we go again into Egypte? And thus they ſayde on to another let vs make a Captayne ouer vs, and go agayne Into Egypte. Marke here the the vnfayfullnes of the ſo Meſſen, gers Beholde alſo the weake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:13"/>fayth that was in the people. The word of the lord bad moyſes ſend ſpies into the land (which the lord wold geue to the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el) as yt was often promyſed before, But theſe meſſengers loked vpon the mighty men &amp; great gyauntes, and forgat the promyſe of god.</p>
            <p>Lykewyſe the people herkened to the voice of the meſſengers and let the voyce of the lord go. Oh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythful generacyon. Where was Abrahams fayth? whych when he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to kyll hys onely ſonne,<note place="margin">Gen. xxii</note> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord had promiſed to bleſſe al nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he forſoke, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon left hys owne wyſdome, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lord wold raiſ him again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to lyf rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his word ſhuld not be fulfiled. This is wryt ten for oure learnynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, we alſo maye ſet hande of the promyeſes of god with lyke faith.<note place="margin">is</note> But where thys fayth? let vs nowe talke
<pb facs="tcp:4364:14"/>awhyle of our latter dayes, that we maye ſe whether thys fayth be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs or not. Many wryters haue compared the Pope to kyng Pharoo of egypte. And in dede yt may welbe: for as long as he gouerned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche: he made vs bond ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, he and hys mynyſters. Yea we were ſo blyndly ledd and ſo tyraun nouſly handled, and that with ſuch vylany: that I am ſure, the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes were neuer ſo ſhameful intre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated of kyng Pharoo and hys my nyſters: As we haue byn of thys Phatao and his ſhauen genetaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the dayes hath bene that yf a manne hadd fownde a Preſte or A F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yer in the vedde wythe Hys wyffe: He durſte not to haue lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hys Handes vpon hym. Where as y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yt hadd bene another mann all thoughe He hadd ſtayne hym? yt hadd bene accoumted no fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lte at all. No mann myghte haue
<pb facs="tcp:4364:14"/>ſewed them at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law. Ye, thes egyptyans were wexed ſo proude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had deuyded theim ſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore iſraelites, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei muſt be called ſpirituall fathers and we the lewde people. And yf any poore Iſraelyte had grudged at anytime to bear ther heavy and intollerable but thens: there was no remedy but cruel death with out mercy. Onles he wold ſweare to be obedient vnto theim in All thinges whaſoeuer they ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund him. Many a pore ſoule hath ſuffred vnderthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt cruell torments. Many a one haue they put to death y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> could not be ſuffred to anſweare for them ſelf many a one haue they put to death the cauſe where of was neuer knowen. Many a one haue they murdred i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priſon ſecretly leſt there outragius cruel ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlaghter ſhuld be ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>li knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>but tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks be vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighti god which of his loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he
<pb facs="tcp:4364:15"/>bare vnto vs, at the cryes of ſome faythful Iſraelytes, hath delyuerd vs, by hys miniſter Kyng Henry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viii, from vnder the great &amp; intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable burthens of this cruel pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rao, &amp; hath brought vs into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſ, where we heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſpeak to vs dayly, in the bible, wherein is wryten both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> newe teſtament &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde, is brought amonge vs, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raos power is taken from him: hys bulles be not regarded, his ſuperſty oyous ſeetes of relygyon be gone &amp; agreate meany of his mahometrye &amp; other baggage did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthey king henry deſtroye. Many wonderfull thynges dyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord brynge to paſſe in his dayes, yet lo for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, coulde not we contynew faythful. Al theſe wonders the prophecyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde him ſelfe agaynſt thoſe falſe prophe tes, nor yet the examples of thos iſraelytes in the wyiderneſſe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wlde kepe vs in a ſtedfaſte fayth
<pb facs="tcp:4364:15"/>In the promyfes of the lorde, but at euery temptation we were ready to go back agayne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Egipte. For yf there came but a commaundement to burne our bokes, or ſuche lyke: ſtrayghtway we began to dyſpayre to grudg, and murmur, ye, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny went backe againe into Egypt, and benot yet returned. Rather had they to be ſlaues in Egypte, to ſytte by the fleaſh pottes, fyllyng their luſtes: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ieopred theire liues at the commaundement of god, in the wylderneſſe. And for ſuch i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fy delity &amp; wickednes, how haue we felt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, both hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger peſtilence &amp; war. But they wyl ſay, it hapneth onely, for theſe new fownd oute He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be now abroad. And euery euell that chauncethe, they impute it to the Goſpel, whyche they cal He reſye. Yet thys I am ſure, All they can not denye: But theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues in the wylderneſſe happened
<pb facs="tcp:4364:16"/>vnto the people, for dyſobeyng the word of the lord, and for walkinge after ther owne in uencions. Now yf theſe (whom they call heretikes) go aboute to ſet vp, or put downe any thynge byſyde the doctryne of chryſte: then myghte they haue ſome couller to cloke their matter withal, to make the rude people be leue that theſe plages belonged not to theyr vnfaythfull workes. But now to contyrme ther malyce they ſay: Loke vpon their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge. Here ys one preacheth aſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at fore none and ys drou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k at after none. Another i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ahole aſſeble makethe an oratyon to deſtroye vyce: and forthe wythe a conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nente committeth abhomynacion. One wryttethe in boke thys daye to exhorte men to good lyuynge:</p>
            <p>And the nexte daye him ſelfe ys fownde an opene tranſgreſſoure of the lawe. Loke vpon them
<pb facs="tcp:4364:16"/>(ſay they) greatter whroekepers &amp; adulterers, greater ſueare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; blaſ phemers of the name of god, gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter extorcyoners and deceauers, more proude, more enuyous more couetous then theſe (whych talke ſo much of the goſple) can not, nor ys poſſyble to be. But what ſhall we ſaye to them now? ſhall we ſaye they lye? no, for they ſpeake many thinges truli (although thei ſpeak yt of malyce) as I haue ſene the experyence to ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But alas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euer ſuche manyfeſt wyckednes ſhulde be ſuffred vnpunyſhed. Loke to yt (O ye Magyſtrates) for ryght ſharpe iudgement ſhalbe done on theſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be in auctorite:<note place="margin">ſape. vii.</note> and it pertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to your charge, as well to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yntayne chriſtes doctryne in puni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhynge the wycked lyuynge, As to deſtroye I dolatrye In aboly ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge falſe preachynge.</p>
            <p>Therfore I ſaye a gayne loke to
<pb facs="tcp:4364:17"/>yt. For thes falſe baalams be not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able to open theire mouthes wyth learnyng to defende their falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne. For euery chyld almoſt is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to confound theim, euen by their owne learnyng, and Doctors. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now do they ſlander the goſpell, wyth the fylthy lyuyng of a ſorte of falſe faiued brethren, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their lyppes confeſſe chryſte the lord, but in ther dedes they deny him openly,<note place="margin">Tit. i.</note> and that vnpunyſhed. And therfor yet once agayne (thoughe I be but a poore, and vnprofytable ſeruaunt of Ieſus chriſte) do I exhort you (O ye Magyſtrates and hygh rulers.<note place="margin">Nu. xxv</note> in the zeale of Phinees, that due punyſhment maye be had for ſuche outeragyous wickednes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent that the Lorde maye the ſonnet wythedrawe hys plague from vs, and hys mercye take place in repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunte hartes by faythe converted. Due punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I ſay, for I feare
<pb facs="tcp:4364:17"/>me exhortacion wyll not ſerue, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes is ſo greate. And I beſeche you (o ye Magyſtrates) that yow wyl pardon me of ſo much boldnes that I may exhort you alſo to take hede that there be not in any of you an euel hart of vnbelefe to departe from the lyuing god: for I am ſure the deuel goeth aboue lyke a rori<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">i. petre. v.</note> ſekyng whom he may deuoure: therefore take hede. For yf any of you be geuen to deſyre and couette to reing with ryches and poſſeſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this world: He wyl be at ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd withe you, in ſuch wyſe wyl he perſwade you, that you ſhal thinke ye can not haue to muche to ſette furhe Chryſtes Goſpell. Yf anye of youe, be geuen to the luſt of we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: He ſhalle perſwade your (by the ſcryptures ye ſhall thynke) that yow may take another by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde your wyfe. Orells put away youre wyfe, and marye another
<pb facs="tcp:4364:18"/>for euery faulte, Though you your ſelf be the cauſe of her fal. Yf any of you be geuen to pryde, thys wycked ſerpente ys alway at hande to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwade you, that foraſmuche as ye be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aucthoryte, ye ought to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen abue other men. Thus ſhall he brynge into you a certayne loue of your ſelf, and ye ſhal thinke that you be lyft vp aboue other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che yet be your brethreu. Yf you be geuen to be angrye, he ſhall cauſe you in a fury to forget mercy, yea &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal your autoryte be aminiſter of ſin. Do what vyce ſoener you be bent to, heys redy to i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>creaſe yt and to make you forget yt: And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for lacke of exhortacyons, may ye be hardened in youre ſynne, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ys yt dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous. Take hede therfor, for a li<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleſin i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you is much noted of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: and in thos thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ye fall Yourefalſes, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye punyſh other? So by thys meanes maye
<pb facs="tcp:4364:18"/>yt come to paſſe that ſynne ſhall not be punyſhed. Thus ſhal theſe backbyters haue alway an occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſlaunder Chryſtes goſple. For they forget not the euel lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, that they maye ſpye in theſe Goſpelers. But I aſke theſe holye Fathers, whene theye ſay theſe goſpellers lyue ſo naughtyly in al kynde of ſynne and abhomynacyons: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doo they hate the Synne, that theſe menne commytte: Or ells the goſpell, that they ſo much talke of? Nay, the ſinne wyl they ſaye for verye ſhame. But yf ſynne be be the cauſe, why theye ſaye thes goſpelers be ſuch horemongers ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuche ſwerars, ſuch prowde menne ſuche coueteous perſons et. cc. Yf Theſe Be the Cauſes: Why hadd they not made Statutes (When they bare the Rule) and ſtrayghte Lawes, to Punyſhe Theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4364:19"/>abhominacions with ſome puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes at leſt as wel as they made lawes to punyſh with death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alked, preached, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any thinge out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> defence of chryſtes goſple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Ipoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ytys and falſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yne? yea why do they not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e owle vpon theſe Abhomy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yous in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deferentſye in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>enne Seing euen of ther owne ſecte be as fylthye lyues and as wycked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s The other, and A greater number? ye the holy fathers them ſalues wylbe knowen to be no ſayilles (I warante ye we) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umtyme. But wyll ye know the cauſe why the goſple preacheth A g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynſte there Ipocryſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, A ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſte there ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et couſnes, Agaynſt their p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and daylie gloryt: And Agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſte theyte blyndeneſſe ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye in godes worde: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te all there abhomynacyons
<pb facs="tcp:4364:19"/>The goſple, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt illud hinc illi clamores. Heceſt illa ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liiia. Thys is the thynge they be a greued with all. Howe carefull therefore and ware, oughte they to be in theyr conuerſacyon, that ſhale preache, Teach, wryt or reade or with authoryty ſet forth goddes worde vnto the people for they be as it were meſſengers ſent to ſpye owte the land. How had they nede to take hede that there be in none of them an euell harte of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue to departe from the lyunge God: leſt thorowe Infydelyte they Brynge Ane euelle reporte vpon the lande of Canuaan. We are Admonyſhed here bye Theſe meſſengers to cleaue faſte to the worde of god: To ſtycke, to hys promyle be to dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gence in owre vocatione. And to forſacke owre o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne woſdome Ye: and to do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ely which he commaundeth. For yf
<pb facs="tcp:4364:20"/>the word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſayd; deſtroye the Images of baall, plucke doun the Idols,<note place="margin">iiii Re. xx iii.</note> deſtroy the hylaulters, burne the groues, leaue nothynge feare theme not, I ame the lorde. What councelle is there (In thys caſe) that may be allowed. Hathe not the lorde ſayede to Moyſese ſende menne to ſpye oute the lande whiche I wyl geue to the children of Iſrael?<note place="margin">Heb. iii</note> Vnderſtand (deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne) that as Moyſes the choſen ſeruant of god to whom was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted the gouernaunce of the chyldren of Iſrael to rule In the leter. Doth ſygnyfye the onely begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne of god Ieſus Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, to whom is committed al Iudg went rule and powe owt al mene in his ſpirite:<note place="margin">Geue. xv. Hed. vii.</note> Aod as Melchyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech kyng of ſalem the hye preſte of god withowet begynnynge or endynge: doth paynt before owre
<pb facs="tcp:4364:20"/>eyes the euerlaſtyng preſthod of chryſte, whych offred the true brede and the true wyne,<note place="margin">Heb. iiii.</note> of whyche whoſo eateth and drynketh: hath euerlaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyffe: ſo doth this holi land promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyd to Abraam and hys poſteryte ſygnyfy vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy promiſed dwellynge of the father, that heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manſyon prepared of chryſte for this elect, that kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in which ys ioy and peace i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſte.<note place="margin">Hebre. x.</note> Theſe are the ſhadowes of good thynges is come, and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther nation ſayeth ſayut pauie) &amp; thys land of Canaan) whyche was promiſd to abraam and to his ſeed and they poſſeſt yt in dede was but a ſhadowe of the euerlaſtynge kyngdome of heuen. The Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wildernes: betok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th thys myſerable lyffe, ſo ful of tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ubles and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacyon. And as all ſuche as grudged a gaynſte god in the wylderneſſe when any temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon
<pb facs="tcp:4364:22"/>aroſe, and wold go back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn into egypt: dyed in the wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and were not ſuffrede to enter into the lande of canaan: cuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo are all ſuche vnfaythfull, and fleſhly lyuers, as can not abyde to haue their luſtes reſtraned but wold go agayne into egypte by the fleſh pottes, and all ſuch as wyll not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde by the worde of the lord, to worſhyppe him accordynge as he hath appoynted, but wold go after ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g goddes worſhiping hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>after ther owne inuentyons: all theſe I ſaye (oneles they repent and be conuerted) ſhall not enter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, but ſhal lye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ys, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of euerlaſting trouble &amp; vexacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Take hede ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore there be not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of you a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euel harte of vnbelefe. Let vs not ſhrynkee In thys wyllderneſſee but pacyentelye abyde the wyll of god and then be we ſure we
<pb facs="tcp:4364:22"/>ſhall poſſeſſe thys trutefull lande: for god hath promiſed, and that ys ſufficient. Loke what he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken muſt nedes come to paſſt, and (god ys mi wytneſſe) I dyd euer ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e I had any perſeaueraunce i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es doctryn, beleue, that as the pope was depriued of his falſe vſurped poure: ſo ſhuld al hys fayned rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de caye, and be vtterly deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For the lord ſayeth:<note place="margin">Math. XV.</note> euery plant whych my heauenly father hathe not planted ſhall be pluckede vp bye the rootes. Not wythe ſtane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, yt hathe come forthe fayre and eaſylye, and peraduenture ſome of theſe vnfaythefull. Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengerse hathe broughte An euell report vppon thys heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Canaan, whyche ys the verye doctryne of. Chryſte,<note place="margin">What. xiii</note> as chryſte callethe yt hym ſelfe. For I haue hearde ſome ſaye (whyche haue bene no ſmall fooles) it ys good
<pb facs="tcp:4364:23"/>in ſuch wayghtye maters to take good aduyſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and do al thinges with diſcretion. For yf we ſhuld ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olyſhe and put downe al thinges that gods worde doth not allowe, meanyng the abhomynable abuſes of the maſſe, and the greate dyſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of mynyſters with ſuche lyke: greate hooſtes, and greate armyes of men wyll inuade vs: And we ſhall not be able to Indure aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſte them. For here haue we the ſcottesone the one ſyde, the french<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men on the other ſyde. The Iryſh men be brute beaſtes. The pope ſhal ſet the Emperoure vpon vs. And all nacyons wyl in vade vs. Ye owr owne countre wyll rebell agadnſt vs. Oh Caleb Caleb.</p>
            <p>Oh Ioſua, here you not what an euel report this meſſengers bringe vpon the land. Thus &amp; ſuch lyke tales wyll make the people rebell
<pb facs="tcp:4364:23"/>agaynſt Moſes. Why rent you not your clothes? amonge theſe xii. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſengers that were ſent to ſpye out the land: was there but two fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full menne. But theſe two when they ſaw the multytud ſo farre out of order, ſo voyde of grace, that Moyſes and Aaron fell downe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon there faces to intreate them: They rent theyr clothes, and ſpake to the hole congregatyon ſayeng: The land that we haue walked tho row to ſpye oute, ys a very good lande: yf the lorde haue luſte vnto vs, he ſhall bryng vs into the ſame lande and geue yt vs, whyche ys a land that floweth with milke and hony. But in any wyſe rebell not agaynſte the lorde: And feare not the people of thys lande. For we wyl eate them vp as breade. Their defence is departed from them, but y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lord is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, be not affraid of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er. c Marke wel the werdes of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4364:24"/>two faithful Meſſengers, we wyl eate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp as bread ſay they there defence is departed from them, the lorde is wyth vs, be not affrayd, of them. Oh fayth fayth. Yf all theſe landes and coutrees were bent to come i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dede, what ſhould we feare? Rather ſhould we beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of theſe Enymtes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge ouer the Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the hole hooſt ſhuld ſynke: then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſhould faile thoſe that fayth fully truſt in hym. But all thynge muſt be done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſobryete and wyſdom ſaye they. But I pray you what greater wiſdome &amp; dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therbe: then to do erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; ele to ſet forth his truth; what is your minde to do? are ye not myu ded to ſet forth goddes worde with a pure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience? Are you not myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to do accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? is it not your purpoſe to Root out Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie? do you not intend to ſet vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:24"/>treu wourſhipe of god? yf co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be defyled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> coueteouſnes hordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e pryde, or any ſuch lyke vyce: then feare how ye go forward, and take good councel before you procead, for goddes word wyll not cloake y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longe, but wyl doutles ſe it puniſh ed, ye and al men ſhal ſe it. But yf your conſcyence be cleare, and ye ſeake nothing but the onely glory of god (though it were with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of al youre goodes yf it pleſed god ſo to hryng it to paſſe) &amp; to do only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nmundeth your why ſtay ye are ye afrayde of the numbre of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the greate gyauntes? is it not godds cauſe that you take in hand darennynat you bentet vpon ſuch a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not god our ſheld &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue we not apromiſe that v. ſhal chaſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e hundreth,<note place="margin">Le . xxvi Deut. xxx ii.</note> and an .C. ſhall chace tene thowſand? Are theſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yne wordes are they not oure lyfe? do we not ſe here in the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:25"/>ſame ſtory, that when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would haue ſtoned Caleb and Ioſua, for ſpekyng to them in this tayth: the glory of the Lorde appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the tabernacle of wytneſſe vnto the people, And the lorde ſayd vnto Moyſes: How longe ſhall thys people blaſpheme me? And how long wyll it be ere they beleue me, for all the Tokens that I haue ſhewed amonge them? I wyl ſmpte thys people wyth peſtilence, and dyſtroy them, and wyll make of the a greatter and a myghtyer people, then thys ys, ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde. Conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well theſe wordes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder who, ſpake them, to whom they were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and for whoſe ſake they were wrytten. Oh what caſe ſhoulde we be in,<note place="margin">Pſal, cvi.</note> yf oure Moyſes ſtode, not in the gapp, and prayed hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs? How vnfaythfully do we dayly fal, euen as yt were a peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:4364:25"/>that had no god at all? Let vs therefor be warned in tyme. Let vs be conuerted vnto the lorde. Let vs ſeparate oureſelues from the truſt of menne, from the wyſdome of menne, from the vayne confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thys worlde, wyth all the vanytes of yt. And let vs wyth a ſyugle eye and a pure conſcence call vpon the name of the Lorde. Oure medyatour ys alwaye ready to offer out prayers to hys father, and hathe promyſed that we ſhall be hearde, yf we call in fayth.</p>
            <p>Let vs learne of Moyſes and other holy fathers, of Chryſte and hys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles how to praye: For alwayes are there oceaſyons offerede to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythefull Manne to Praye: As was here to Moyſes for the people. But we had nede to praye for oure ſelues &amp; to deſyre oure Moyſes to pray for vs alſo: for we haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded
<pb facs="tcp:4364:26"/>after thys maner. Therefor let vs lyft vp oure boyce ſaiynge: o lorde be mercyfull vnto thy people accor dyng to thyne accouſtomable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes, do away oure offences: For we haue ſynned. But yet for thy names ſake delyuer vs. We haue taken vpon vs to be of thy goſple, and wyth our mouthes we confeſſe the, but in our deades we deny thee: yet lorde haue mercy, for yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhuldeſt plage vs accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to our deſertes: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other vnbeloui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſay: Lo: Behold how God hateth their hereſye, and thus ſhuld thy worde be deſpyſed and hared of al nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s oh be gracyous therefore vnto our ſynnes accorynge to thy greate mercy, lykewyſe as thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne vs alwaye hytherto be thus gracyous vnto vs for chriſtes ſake. Lett all ſuche faythfull men, as do earneſtly ſtudy the amendment of their wycked lyfe, ſay amen. But he
<pb facs="tcp:4364:26"/>that doth not ſo: let him kepe ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce orels ſay our lady Pſalter: for ſuch prayers doth goddes word teache vs, by hys ſayntes, which wer writ ten for oure learnynge. As for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyns mumblers and maſſ mongers with dyryges and trentalles with ſuch ſuperſtious prayers, the ſcry pture ſpeaketh not of theim. But thes &amp; ſuch lyke ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcypture full. No vaine bablynge: but effectuall faythful, &amp; ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ought oure pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers be. For the prayer of a cyghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſous man,<note place="margin">Iaco. v.</note> auayleth much (ſayeth laynct Iames) yf it be feruent. As it appereth alſo i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſtory by Moy ſts, which obteyned grace for the people. For the lord ſayed: I haue forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſayed. But thos y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue murmured agayuſt me, tell them, as truly as I lyue (ſayrth the lorde) I wyll do vnto youe: euen as ye haue ſpoken in myue eares. Your carkaſſes ſhall lye In the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:27"/>wylldernes, and all ye that were numbred frome .xx. yeres and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, whyche murmered agaynſte me ſhall not come into the lande coucecuynge the whyche I lyft vp my hande that I wold let youd wel therein (ſaue caleb the ſonne of Ie phune and Ioſua the ſonne of Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſo ther dyed and were plaged before the lorde all the men whome Moyſes ſent toſpye oute the lande and cam agayn and made the hole multytude to murmure a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aniſt yt becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brought vp a miſreport vpon the lande that yt was euell. Here ſhall yt be very neceſſary to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiepreſtes &amp; pharyſes (whych gathered a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt had raiſed lazarus) &amp; thei ſaied what do we?<note place="margin">Ioh. xii.</note> this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth manytoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s yf: we let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> go thus, al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl beleue in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then ſhal the tomans come and take awaye all oute lande and people. Now with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:4364:27"/>fourty yeres after (as the hiſtories planly declare) was ieruſalem deſt royed in dede of the romans and the moſt part ſlayne and led away captaine. But why trou ye? becauſ they ſuffred chryſte to preach and his doctrine to be publiſhed? not but becauſe they myſtruſted leſt yf they ſhould haue ſuffred him, the romans ſhould com, as they dyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd: Quod verebantur hoc acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit illis. Take hede therefore that there be not in any of you an euell harte of vnbelef to depart from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuyng god. I ſay tak hed, for he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feareth the hore froſt the depe ſnow ſhal fal vpon him, and ſurely yf ye feare the dyſtructyon of your body<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſubſtaunce thorow in fidellte &amp; myſtruſt of goddes mighty ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: it is to befeared leſt he ſhalde ſtroi you both body &amp; ſoule Loke to it al ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holde ſo much of youre polytyk wyſdome, for goddes pleaſure.
<pb facs="tcp:4364:28"/>hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>res, paſſe the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wyſdom and reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He wyll not be meſured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mans polycye. He wyll wourke with hys myghty, powre, wheras ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>notvnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it. For theſe meſſengers that were ſent to ſpye oute the lande, percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the multytud of people which were myghtye, &amp; the ſtronge cityes that were in the land: Agayn conſy deryng the greate gyauntes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were there alſo: thought it could not be that they ſhould get the contre, for it ſtoode not with reaſon. And ther fore murmurede they and wyſhed that they had dyed in egypte, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theymought dye in the wyldernes andeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo it cainto paſſe for the un faythfulneſſe for: they were plaged and dyed in the wylderneſſe As many as murmured. But Ioſua and Caleb were left Alyue and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued by the wonderful powre of god &amp; that becauſe of their ſtedfaſt
<pb facs="tcp:4364:28"/>fayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they had in the promyſes of the lorde. But the people wolds haue ſtoned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for there fayth fulnes. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other .x. loke vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; great cetyes but theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loked vpon the people w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them But alas for the blendenes of the worlde: for as the faiſr prophettes ſys of god &amp; conforted the profetes were alway the gretteſt numbre: ſo were the rude multytude coutynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bent to beleue the more paree and to ſtone crucife burne &amp; hang or with ſdme other cruel tormentrs rydde ſuche all waye As broughe them the truth. As we ſe it euydent in all the holye ſcriptures by the prophets, by chriſte him ſelfe and his apoſtles. And as we haue ſene alſo by good experyence in owre dayes. But the lorde is alway at hand to delyuer thoſe that faythful truſt in him, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth them and helpeth them. For ether he delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rethe<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:21"/>beleue, loked onely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was proceded forth of the mouth of god, and regarded nothing els.</p>
            <p>He dyd not reaſon the matter firſt how he might for another ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n, the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former promes of god might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:21"/>pacyence, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures myght haue hope. They are wrytten for oure learnyng ſayethe ſaynt paule. Yf they be wryttenfor our learnynge it ys reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we know them. Els how ſhal we learn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:29"/>whych I conmaunde the thys day, ſhalbe in thyne hart,<note place="margin">Deut. vi.</note> and thou ſhalt ſhew them vnto thy chyldren, and ſhalt talke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when thou art at home i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thin houſe: And as thou wal keſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waie, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lieſt downe, and when thou ryſeſt vpp, and thou ſhalt bynde them for a ſigne vpon thy hand, &amp; they ſhalbe a warnyng betwene thyne eyes, and thou ſhalt writ the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſtes of thy howſe, &amp; vpon thy gates. etc. Agayn, take hede therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; lawes which I ſet before yow thys daye.<note place="margin">Deut. xi.</note> etc. Alſo, what ſo euer I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> take hede ye do only to the lord, &amp; put you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge thereto, nor take ought ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. etc. Beholde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what care the lorde geueth his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld not be forgote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therefore were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets alway to writ forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wonders y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſhewed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of menne.
<pb facs="tcp:4364:29"/>The lorde ſayed to Ioſua: Let not the boke of the law departe out of thy mouth,<note place="margin">Ioſua. i.</note> but record therein both day &amp; nyght. Now yf theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our hart: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel pleaſure to talke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the mowth talketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboundance of the hart. Yf they be not in our hart nor in our mouth: it is not poſſyble that we ſhould be doinge of them.<note place="margin">Mat. xii.</note> Yf we be not doynge of the lordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: ſurely we tourne to the ryght hand or the lefte: we adde we diminiſhe: we forget y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true wur ſhyp of god: we ferue Idolls &amp; fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our owne iue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions: we forgete Abrahams farth: we forget Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes doctrine: we forgett Caleb &amp; Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſua, Chriſt &amp; all his apoſtles, wyth al their doctrine of pacience, throw whiche we ſhould haue hope. Alas what caſe were we i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when we knew not what, was the olde teſtament
<pb facs="tcp:4364:30"/>nor what was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byble was an vnknowen thynge with in theſe xx. yere Here i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Englande.<note place="margin">iii. Re. xii</note> Ieroboa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had invented vs a new law, a new wurſhype of god, for he knew wel y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> the people would haue ſuch deuoci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on that they muſt nedes haue what to wurſhype, as we ſe by the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elyres i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vildernes whirh aſſone as Moyſes was gone into the mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to talke with the lorde and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, by and by they muſt haue ſome ſymilitude, ſome lykenes of god,<note place="margin">Ex. xxxii</note> ſome on thing or another to directe theyr prayers vnto. And therefore made them a golden calfe and wourſhyped yt. And Ieroboam I ſay knew well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people muſt nedes haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to wurſhyp, and he feared leſt (yf they ſhould go to Ieruſalem to wurſhyp) he ſhould leſe hys kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome agayne, &amp; therefore he made them two golden calfes, In Dan &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4364:30"/>Bethel, Owr Ieroboam lyke wyſe after that he came to that great dig nytye that he was called, Pater Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trum Caput Eccleſie. etc. with ſuch lyke: he knew wel that yf the people ſhoulde know the ſcripture, and be brought vp in the ſymple doctryn of chryſte that he culd neuer conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new ſo prynce lyke cleane contrary to the doctryne theyrof, nor non of hys. Wherefore dylgent ſtudy was had to inuent ſeruyces, wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypyngs, expoſytyes, ſacramentes, wyth all the goodlyeſts Iewelles and coſtly apparell that moughte be had, ſo that at the laſte the hole worlde was rauyſhede wyth that greate holynes. Than became the mynyſters of thys Ieroboam in euery contre the greateſt menne of the world. Noo Realme but Car dynalles were the cheyfe in the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell and ruled the hole Realme,
<pb facs="tcp:4364:31"/>by ſhoppes were Ambaſſators and of the preuer cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſaul. Deanes and prebendaryes were the kynges pheſycya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s chaplens and ſtuardes: Parſons &amp; vy cars wer great Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſtuardes &amp; chaplyns. I ſpeak nothyng of abbottes pryours pro vyncyalls with ſuch a rablemente of cloyſtererss. What dyd all thes did they thach the peoplethe goſple of Ieſus chryſte? dyd they teache the people fayth in chryſt, loue and charyte, meakenes, gentylnese, ſymplycytie ſo bryrte, chaſtyt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralyte, and to diſpyce the worlde and to go thorowe the wyld erneſſe with. Moyſes and Chry ſte theyr to be tryede whethere theyr fayth were Lyke Abrahams, conſtance and lyuely in the promyſes of god? Alas fewe of them cowlde teache Any thonge at all, for they Were (for the moſte) parte greate menes
<pb facs="tcp:4364:31"/>ſonnes brought vp in hawkyng &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng. They knew not the goſple, per adventure they wold ſet there chaplens to preach the maſter of ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence, and the legend horrye, yf he brought I .ii. or .iii. of the doctors, oh what a learned man was that, but theſe great men toke ther plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures. They knew not what fayth ys, but Imagened, that they had fayth when they beleued ther was a god that Ieſus chryſt was hys ſonne and born of the vergyn mari .etc. but now they thought thys to be to lytyl to brynge them to heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and therefore al the maſſe matins. euen ſonges,. Dyryges holye breade holy water, palmes aſhes wythe ſuche Other geare ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be a meane, And ſpeacya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yre newe ſacraments and Idolls that Ieroboam had ſett vp and therefore they helde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlye that faythe onelye cowlde
<pb facs="tcp:4364:32"/>not iuſttifi, nethercould webi faith o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly beaccepted into goddes fauour for they knew not what thys lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayth that abraam had meante letpaule ſai wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>he wil, the churche was aboue pale, and all the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture now was ther lyuyng lyk vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other men, or wurſſe ank the cauſe of al others myſchet for they were as prowde, e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vyous, and mali cyous, as ani men wer in the world yea man had byn better to haue had the dyſy leaſure of .x. other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of them. They fared as wel &amp; had as many daynte dyſhes as any lordes in the realme and more qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes a great deal. This could not be wyth out weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whether they were whoremongers, adulterers &amp; wurſe, let all the world be iudge. Noman roughte more to be alofte in the world then thei did: and ſuch greate houſes, horſes houndes ſho tynge dyſynge, open houſetor gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne,
<pb facs="tcp:4364:32"/>ther ſeruantes In veluet and chaynes of gold. What tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatyon they had in in the wylder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes I can not tel, onles they were tempted with ladyes and gentyll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women that vyſyted them. But ſure they tempted other and mad them go thorow the wyldeenes and thorow the fyre alſo. Alas they had no mercy vpon a poore wreche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> once opened his mowth agaynſt them, but cryed owte herytike he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytyke, burne, burne, fagotts, fyre But hys examynatyons was not harde of the lay people for feare. Alas Yf the lord had not lefte vs ſede: We ſhulde haue bene, As ſodome, and lyke vnto Gomorra.<note place="margin">Pſal. ii.</note> Be wyſe therfore (o ye kynges) be learned ye that be Iudges of the erth, leſt the lorde be angrye with yow and ye peryſhe from the ryght way. But kynges were alway as kepte dionge wyth warres Yf
<pb facs="tcp:4364:33"/>they had any learnynge, and lyke to ſmell out any of their wyies, or yf he wold reforme any thig. Loke how thy handled king Iohn. Tho mas becket was one oi their ſaints but gentell teader loke vpon hys liff in the legend the boke of ſaints lyues. I am ſure they haue wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beſt thei cowld for him, but yet marke yt well. There was noman mought ſtudy the ſcrypture before he had bin Maſter of art, and then was yt nothinge worth tyll he had ſtudyed the doctors, counſels, and decrees, the whych ys more thena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ys able to do in all hys lyffe though he lyue. Lxxxx. yere and to ſaye hys ſeruyce beſyde, whyche all preſtes were bownd to doo on payne of dampnacyon. Thys I ſpeake of our doctors in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiberſytees: As for oure preſtes in the contree: the dayes hathe byn that be was coumptedd a greate
<pb facs="tcp:4364:33"/>clarke that coulde tell whome he ſhoulde ſerue to morowe. They knew not what the byble meanthei were not acquanted wyth the new teſtament. Some of them thought yt ſhuld be hetyſy becauſe yt was called the new teſtamente. For this worde now offended then greatly But now they be well amended for ſome of them wylbe able to reade Englyſhe wythyn a whyle though yt before aganſt ther wyl. I know wel they can not abyd the hearing of this,<note place="margin">Ma. xxii</note> nomeor then theſcribes and pharyſes cowld a byde chryſt when he ſayed wo be vnto you ſcrybes &amp; pharties for ye ſhit vp the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of godbefore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. etc. but weper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture they wyl ſay, we denynot chryſte put we wurſhyp Chrpſte and therefore we kyll them that wyll nott beleue in Chryſte.</p>
            <p>But ſaieth Chrſte: tak hede that no man decaue yow. For ther
<pb facs="tcp:4364:34"/>ſhall many come and ſaye: I am chryſt and ſhall deceaue many: but when ye ſe the abhomynacyon of deſolacyon ſtond in the holy place .etc. then yf any man ſhal ſaye vnto you: lo here ys chriſt, beleue yt not. Ieroboam was not ſo madd to ſay ye ſhal beleue no more tn the lorde but in ſtraunge goddes:<note place="margin">Re. xii</note> but he ſai ed yt ys muche for you to go to Ie ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behold therfore theſe ſhalbe youre goddes. etc. hys meanynge was that they ſhoulde do to theſe godes the ſame wurſh yppe that they dyd before at Ieruſalem. And our Patryarkes. Pretend Chriſt altogether. But the wurſhype that he preſcrybed vnto vs was gone. Hys Docrryne wyth all the ſcryptures had they locked fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs ſo that none of vs durſtloke vp on yt in the tonge that we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtod, ſo that we could haue but ſmall hope thorow comfort of the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:34"/>ſceyptures. Alas how was yt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ſhould be obedyent vn to the voyce of oure lorde god and walke in hys wayes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we knew them not, nor coulde we tell what they meant: but moſt harti humble and Immortal thankes be geuen to the almighti god, which thorow the merytes and prayer of oure mer cyfull Moyſes, hathe ſturred the harte of noble king henry the .viii to deſtroye the abhomy nacyons of thys wycked Ieroboam. But chefly of al other thynges (as we are moſte bownde ar thys tyme) ou ghte we to lawde and prayſe the lord whych of hys te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der loue lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs a you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Ioſias which (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace &amp; power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) ſhal (thorow his godligoueruour &amp; counſellers (fyniſh the building of the holy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple whych his father beganne accordynge to the patron y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath perſcrybed ithegoſple
<pb facs="tcp:4364:35"/>of has onely ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Ieſus cryſte our lorde. Ho wbeit we are not yet paſte the wyld etneſſe, we are not yet ente red the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Canaan: for althoghe the lorde haue &amp; doth dayly plage ſuch vnfaythfull meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, which haue not erneſtly beleued hys word but feared men more then god: yet ceaſeth not temptatcyons, troubles grudginges &amp; murmuringes. For ſom wrig &amp; wreſtto go backe agayn ito Egypt &amp; do as ther forefathers haue done, for ther is ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey of gold &amp; ſyluer meate &amp; drynke, there mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght we fyl our belyes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhpot tes. Ther was more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty (ſay they) of all maner of thinges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oue toune the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is now i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a whol ſhire: more mirth &amp; paſtim i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on day, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is now in a whoe yere. It was neuer mery ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this new learni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. Thys ſay they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcarcyte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyldernes, nor any te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de ſerte. a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>other ſort (which be polytik
<pb facs="tcp:4364:35"/>men t)hey wolde forth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good wil for they care not, which end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtat go forwarde: ſo they mighte not be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; might alſo get ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what byit Thes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſraid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ites mo abitesamorites w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſpecially the Enyckes, which be great Giaunts. The byſhop of Ro me is agreat ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; hath done many fetes of armes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his dayes. I knowe wel his biſhoppes &amp; other prelates beare agreat ſtroke yet in many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees. But what ſayeth Ioſua and Caleb: Their ſhadowe is departed from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the lord is with vs feare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not therfore. And ſurely (as is ſayed) yf your conſcyence be clere ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yow ſeke nothig but the glory of god: yow nede not feare men. But nou is ther another ſort of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch after they perceaued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god had ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly plaged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grndgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g people for their vnfaithfulnes, ſuch as wold go back agai ito Egypt: i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they perceued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iord wold haue
<pb facs="tcp:4364:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>them go forewarde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quere the land: theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comero Moiſesther Gouernouer and captayne and ſay lo we be here and wyll go vp vnto the place of whych thelord hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to vs. For we haue ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned But Moyſes ſayed: why go ye on thys be yonde the word of the lord it wyl not com wel to paſſe wyth you, go not vp therefore. etc. but they wold forth euen i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the toppe of the hyll there was no remedy, &amp; there were all ſlayne. Very notable ys thys place for vs and worthy to be had in remembraunce. For here maye we perceaue howfro ward &amp; vnruly the multytude of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are alway to be obed ye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the voyce of the lord eueri wai ar we pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; redi to falfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of peare, thei were not ſofar f y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but now thear as far on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſt ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d they wer not ſo ſlacke before, but now ther beas haſti, &amp; al beſyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. We haue ſinned ſai thei: and whiſo? verely be
<pb facs="tcp:4364:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>cauſe they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god but grutched &amp; now they were commaunded to tarye and not go, &amp; yet they went. Theye thought to haue made amendes &amp; marred altogether. A good leſſone is this alſo, for our good intentes What ſo euer is done of a good in tent ſay oure fathers is merytory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And it is playne that theſe men went forth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a good intent, &amp; yet were ſlayne, becauſe they harkened not to the voyce of the lorde, wich ſpake vnto them by his Prophet Moyſes, as he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, daily to vs by chriſt &amp; al the prophetes and apoſtles, Take hede therfore therbe not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of you an euel hart of vnbelefe to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god. But theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; were ſory, they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted. Yea they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to error. They wold not go forth be fore at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of god &amp; now they wold not tary at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, but forth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtay or let. Some ther bey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perceue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope &amp; hys gard to haue ledd vs blyndly thys many yeres into a ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true wurſhip of god. And now therefore w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out al ad uyſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wold deſtroialtogether &amp; care not whether ther be any myny ſters or no, ſo they may haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes &amp; benefyces of theſe blynde guydes. they care not whether ther be any i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their rome or no, or whether godes word be preached, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts mi nyſtred or uo: I mean not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. vif. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe caterpyllers whych do all for lucre but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtes ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which he hath ordeyned to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme our faith i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> word. but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſay be ſo haſty foreward to kil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> can anites &amp; other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, becaus thei wold haue their pleſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to dwel i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it balik: for they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t beſid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. Many ther be that get ſpyrytual
<pb facs="tcp:4364:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>landes and poſſeſſyons probendes benefices into their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, but how many be there that labour in aman of good knowleg, to enioye ſuche lyuynge? no fye (ſaye thei) yt ys pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that euer he ſhould be trubled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yt: For the poſſeſſions and rytches doo corrupte eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beſt preachers (as yt hath happened in dede) But alas good men how careful be thei to good preachers, to prouide that thei be not corrupte withe greate lyuings, but I meruayle thei haue no pety vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf. I promiſe you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yff good preachers whiche haue knowledge in chryſtes doctrine and haue bene tyed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wildernes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouble &amp; temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yf thei I ſaie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wel vſe theſe riches &amp; poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s accordingly, but muſt be corrupted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhalbehard tomak mebeleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you which haue not ſomuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nether hath you y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith binſo wel tired ſhuld vſe them wyth
<pb facs="tcp:4364:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>owt a corrupte conſcyence, whyche ſhalbe to your owne damnatyon. Take hede therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ther be not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of you an euel hart of vnbelefe to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lyuynge god. And remembre that ſaynt Paull ſayeth coueteouſnes is y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> roote of al euel. I would to our lord men knew and would conſyder what a ſtrayte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conynge we ſhall all be called vnto, where we ſhal anſwer for the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of euery farthyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to our gouerna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nce, Then ſhal we ſay alas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euer I tok ſuch paynes &amp; trauaile for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which now is beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e myn euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but what ſhuld it avail to ſpeak againſt that vice of couete ouſnes? nothinge at al. And this is one cauſe that maketh many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haſt ſo faſt forewarde. But theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that came to Moyſes &amp; would go ſo freſhly agaynſt their enymies went vp ito y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mowntain. Moyſes bade
<pb facs="tcp:4364:38"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tary &amp; take the lorde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhold ſped the better, but they wold not tary, for they had byn to ſtowe to go foreward at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ndeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, &amp; therefore, now they wold make more haſt, wher as befor they had beleued to enter into the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their Idle inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſuperſticious vaine worckes (or at leſt way they thought them amean the rather to obtaine), And therfore grutched at the doctrin of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel &amp; thought it a new ſcole inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by theſe new felowes (as they teyrme) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the mother holi churche: now they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verted from that popiſh faith, &amp; begyn to runne ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mowntaine at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt daiſh, whether Moyſes wil or no, And they ſay: yf I be predeſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be ſaued: I ſhalbe ſaued, do I neuer ſo euel. Yf be predeſtined to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned: I ſhalbe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned do what I wyl, &amp; ſay any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what his wyl.
<pb facs="tcp:4364:39"/>wherfor let vs be mery and let god worke. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (onles god of his immite goodnes &amp; mercy cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grace) I may thinke wellinough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they be veſſels of wrath ordeyned to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very brut beſtes deſtytute of all grace &amp; wiſdoo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too. And although I wil not ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt: yet ſurely it is gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t blaſphe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y, with ſuch ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tnes or raſhnes without diſcretic<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lblenes of mid to talk of y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hygh predeſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>atyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god. but I let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſſe as thos who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al wyſ me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>honeſt &amp; lerned do vtterli abhor But ther by other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which cly me not fully ſo high, as thes. But how much they differfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other I cane not tell. Thes be ſuch ſort of men which hold y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth is ſufficyent ſo y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no wurckes are neceſſurily requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to our iuſtitycatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi</note> Truth it is we nedenoworcke of our oune to be iuſtified or to bemade righteous i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of god, for it is y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> work of god to beleue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: that
<pb facs="tcp:4364:39"/>is Ieſus chriſt, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which faith on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly we are iuſtified in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of god. But is it not neceſſary trowye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I declare this faithe to my brethren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>els why ſayth chriſt eueri good tre bringeth forth good fruies. etc.<note place="margin">Ma. vii</note> &amp; by ther frut ye ſhal know them. Yf you wil ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you declar your faith to your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your mouth &amp; ſay ye beleue, &amp; yet do not y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> workes of belefe. chriſte ſaieth to yow not al they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſay lord lod ſhal e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>toy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but he y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth my fathers wil which is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The lord is no ſuch idle or vai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ckma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leteth trees which ſhal bere no frut, for dowtles his good trees ſhal bryng forth good frute onles they be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp before ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er &amp; ſpring tim com, &amp; whiſo? to reward or reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penc his maker of his benefites? no no. He careth not for our rewardes nor reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penc, but he doth it becaus we ſhaldo good to his houſhold &amp; declar to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what goodnes I hane reciueed at the lordes haude: for
<pb facs="tcp:4364:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:41"/>ther takes, that euery membre mig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ht do good one to anothre, he aſkeh nothinge but thankes, but al is for owre own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte that we ſhuld helpe eche other with ſuch loue as he hath ſhowed vnto vs, by doing wher we declare our electyone in chryſt and make owre callyng ſure there is no man that loueth hartely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>but he hath pleaſure to do the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that deliteth him whom he loueth, that he mought ſeal his fryndſhip to contyew. contyneu in my loue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (ſayeth chryſt) yf ye ſhal kepe my commaundementes ye ſhal hyde in myloue, euen as I haue kepte my fathers emomaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and byd in hys loue. Here wyl they obiecte and ſay, that foraſmuche as ſaynte Iohn ſaeth yf we ſay that we haue no ſynne: we deceaue our ſelues &amp; the truth is not in vs: Yt were but pharyſaycal pryd to ſeake to be ſo vpryght in the law, as though we
<pb facs="tcp:4364:41"/>coulde be withowte fault for we ſhall be ſynners do what we wyll.<note place="margin">Rom. iii.</note> And Saynt Paul ſaeth we holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a aman is Iuſtylyed by ſayth with cute ehe workes of the lawe. And Peter ſayth thorow faith doth god puryfy the hartes. Whereforyf we haue fayth it is ſuffye tent.<note place="margin">Act. xv.</note> Yf theſe men dyd truly vnderſtand fayth: They ſhuld know that it is alyuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nge thing, a myghtre thinge wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckynge by loue,<note place="margin">Gale. v.</note> that faytize dothe ſaynt Paul mean to the galathya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s where as he excludethe al thinges ſaue faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which faith (ſayeth he) is myghtye in wurckynge by loue. As we ſe how it wroughe in abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and al the holy fathers. For if abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not bin obedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the voyce &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god as we rede of him: how ſhuld it haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo much knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his fayth was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto for ryghteouſnes yf Caleb &amp; Ioſua, had not declared
<pb facs="tcp:4364:42"/>ther faith to the people how could we haue learned by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be faith ful? one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſercheth the ſcryptures and fi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth there: thus ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord And then ſearche his own polityke wytte and weyeth the matter with his owne reaſon whether it ve beſt to do ſo or no, as the lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: doth thys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wurcke by fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th? another lykewyſe ſercheth the ſcryptures and fyndeth ther: thus ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. He ſaieth yf I beleue it is ſuffycient: doth thys man wu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rck by faith? or doth he know what fayth is? is fayth ſuche a common thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue it whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wyll? or hath euery man fayth that hath redde in the ſcryptures? no, uor many which hane great kn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owlege in the ſcryptutes: for many can teache other the lyberty of the goſpel: but they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of corruptyon. Yet theſe men imagen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue fayth that
<pb facs="tcp:4364:42"/>iuſtifyeth. But fayth is not mans imagynatyon. For how can they haue the iuſtyfyenge fayth,<note place="margin">ii. Thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that conteynew in extortyon and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wordome and adultery in enuy and wrath, exceſſe and dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keneſſe, blaſphemy and periury, or in wycked ſuperſtytyon and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, with all kynde of abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natyon? wolde ye haue me thinke thys man to haue the iuſtyfyinge faythe no, no.<note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> For beſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger or vncleane perſon, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteous perſon (which is a wurſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yper of ymages) hath no eherytau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the kyngdome of chryſte and God. Let no mane deceaue yowe with vayne wordes, for becauſe of theſe, commethe the wrath of god vpon the chyldedrone of vnleife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etc. All theſe euill wourkers be the chyldren of vnbelefe. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baoſt of fayth: let them boſt of the goſpel Yea let them caſt owt thes deuilels
<pb facs="tcp:4364:43"/>of other men in the name of Chriſt: yet ſhal he ſaye vnto them Ineuer knew you, depart from me ye wur kers of iniquite. The Iewes boa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted them ſelues to be abrahams chyldren. But Chryſt ſayed vnto them if ye were abrahams chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye wolde do the deades of abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here vnto pertayneth that of ſaint Iames where he ſayeth: Ye ſe then how that of deades a man ys ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfyed and not of faythe oneli. For althoughe abrahams faythe were knowen Inough unto god, why ch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſercheth the in warde pattes and Iuſtyfyeth the harte yet cowld not we haue ſeen hys ſo greate fayth, onles yt had bvn declared by ſome outward worke which mought aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettayn vs alſoof his iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>br faith and although we be iuſtified<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of god byfayth onli (which is alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyft of god) yet is it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſari y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we declarour faith to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>by oure obedyence to the wyll and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of god (and notb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) the eommaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of popes and byſhoppes) what a greate gyft I haue receaued of the lorde, that I mought the rather provoke them to do lykewyſe, For other wyſe we can not beioyned together in one faith. For my brothers faith ys vn certayn to me: onles Ife the frutes of yt appeare, although god know the harte. Therefore ſayeth ſaynte Iames ſhewe me thy faythe by thy deades and I wyll ſhewe my fayth by my deades. And then as the belefe of the harte Iuſty fyeth before god: So do the workes of faythe Iuſtyfy before men. That ys doth declare oure Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy catyon vntomen. Thys ys plain by ſaynte Iames wordes when he ſayeth fayth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out deides is dead, &amp; agayn: ye ſe how fayth wrought whis deades ſo did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dedes ſpring
<pb facs="tcp:4364:44"/>of faith for faith was the wurkers Thus do we make. Paule and Iames agree. For wheras ſaynte Paule exeludeth (as ys ſayed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) all maner of workes, euen the vert wurkes of the lawe in iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catyon, that iuſtificatyon myghte come by the onely fayth in Ieſus Chryſte: euen here doth he declare what fayth he meaneth: fayth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he whych by loue ys mighty in operacyon. Yf yt be no wurkynge fayth: it ys not the fayth that ſaint Paule ſpeaketh of.<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> Take he dether fore brethren that there be not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of yow an euell harte of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe to departe from the lynynge god. Take hede I ſaye and be not deceaued: for faythe ys not ſo ſmall a tryfle as men eſteme ytt. For to ſaye faythe onely Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyethe ys ſone ſpoken, But to knowe the. Wurkynge off
<pb facs="tcp:4364:44"/>yt, and howe yt apprehendeth the mercy of god offred vs in Chryſte: ys a greate matter. Forthys fayth that we ſpeake of when we ſaye fayth onely iuſtyfyeth: ys a lyuely thynge (as ys ſayed) whych wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by lone in the holy goſt, For there ys no ſynne raynynge in our mortall bodyes but thys fayth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulteth yt, &amp; by lytyle &amp; lityle dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uethyt a way. As whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we begynne to wax carefull for the thynges of the world, to couett aboundaunce of rytches: faythe ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ma. v</note> Be not carefull what he ſhall eate or what ye ſhall drynke. etc. Care not for tomorowe and ſo forthe, as for aboundaunce, howe cane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull man be quyett wythe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowndaunce ſeynge hys brother in neceſſite? what faith hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whyche ſorowethe nott ate hys neyghbours greiffe? howe doth he ſorow for his neighbours greif y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4364:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>laboureth for hys owne priuat pro fyte withowte any reſpecte of hys neyboures neceli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Wher be not theſe men that ſeake al to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the greate loſſe &amp; hurte to the neibours? where is fayth which byloue is myghty in operacion: yf we be idle &amp; ſeke not one way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to profyte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meu wealth. faith ſayeth. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweate of thy br<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owes ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> eate thy bread, and he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laboreth not ſhal not eate etc. yf I loue my neyboure as my ſelfe: howe can I be idle al day, &amp; at eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate my brothers ſupere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hathe ſoore laborde for al day. It is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſmal ioue truly. But who wyl yet labour and may be Idle? or yf they do laboure, what labour do a greate numbre of men ſtudy how they may get a way al that be longeth to the poore: To them ſelf Truly it were better theye were Idle. A las where is fay the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:45"/>which by loue ys myghty in operacyon? yf we begynne to wax prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to exalt ourſelfe aboue oure bre thren fayth ſayeth he that exalteth him ſelf ſhal be brought lowe,<note place="margin">Ma. xxiii. Luc. xii.</note> But who ſeaketh not to be vppe? learne of me ſayethe Chryſte for I am meake he that wyll be greate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge you ſhalbe a ſeruaunt, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came not to be ſerued,<note place="margin">Mat. x.</note> but to do ſeruyc. Oh where ys this humylyte and humblenes of mind who couetteth not to rule all men, and wolde be ruled of none? yf god haue geuen rytches poſſeſſyons, auctory te or any lyke benefyte: It is applyed to mayntayne oure pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, to exalte oure ſelues aboueoure brethren. Where ys faith whych by loue ys my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hty in operacyon? Yf we be tempted wythe Enuye and malicſayeth fayth: auenge not youre ſelues, but geue rome to the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:46"/>wrath of god, for ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nce is myn and I wyl rewarde (ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) yea who can ſuffer any iniurye or wronge, &amp; wyl not be rewenged? ye, who can ſuffer him ſelf to be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto, al though he haue deſerued a great rebuk? where ys fayth why ch by loue is mighty i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> operation? Yf we deſire y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> compani vnlaufulli of our neybours wyfe or ſeruaunte faythe ſayeth:<note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> who ſo loketh on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfe luſtynge after her, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted advoutrye alredye in hys harte etc Horekepers and advou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers god wyl iudge. Yet who ys not weary of his owne wyfe &amp; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his neybours? Lyke ſtone hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes (ſayeth Ieremye) euery one neyheth after hys neybours wyfe,<note place="margin">Iere. v.</note> one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly eſtymation refrayneth agreate meny, whoſe wurking are very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete. wher is this rule become? do as ye wold be done vnto. where ys fayth whych by loue is myghty in
<pb facs="tcp:4364:46"/>operation? yf we commit Idolatrie, fayth ſayeth: Thow ſhalt wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe thy lorde god, hym onely ſhalt thow ſerue. Some peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wold aſke me what were Ido latrye? or who commytteth Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye: I ſay, He that wurſhyppe any thynge with out the expreſſe word of god: commytteth Idolatrye. No man hath ſeen god at any tyme.<note place="margin">Iohn. i.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They that wyll wurſhyp god muſt wurſhype hym in ſprete and truth But who wurſhyppeth not viſyble ſpectacles,<note place="margin">Iohn. iiii</note> &amp; creatures in ſtede of they? creator? And ſo robbe god of hys honour? Some do yt for that they wyll not offend theyr brothers conſeyence, ye ratheyr becauſe they wyll not be called heretykes, that is to ſay, a true beleuer i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt, And a louer of hys ddctrine. As Iohu writeth how mani of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe rulers belued on him:<note place="margin">Iohu. xii</note> but becauſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:47"/>Pharyſes they wold not be aknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en of it,<note place="margin">Deut. vi.</note> leſt they ſhould be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nycate, for they loued more the prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then with god. So our men wold ſeme to feare god &amp; loue him, but the feare &amp; loue of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to haue the hyghe place.</p>
            <p>Where ys fayth whyche by loue ys mighty in operatyon? It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be founde, it ys loſt. When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth thynke ye he ſhall fynde fayth on the earth? The old mumſimus wyl not here the word of the lorde but draw backe: the new ſuſtmus be ſo forewarde eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyond the word of the lord, ye they care nomor for the word of the lord the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil ſerue their coueteous luere to fyl ther luſtes, to ſerue for their envyous and cruell mynd, And to lyue in al abhomynatyons. They brynge ſaynt Iohn for them wher he ſayeth: yf we ſay we haue no ſynne we deceaue our ſelf &amp; the
<pb facs="tcp:4364:47"/>truth ys not in vs but why do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre thys ſo wel: verely becauſe that yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne rebuke their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lyfe: they may anſwer with ſaynt Iohn no man ys wyth owte ſynne. But where as ſaynt Iohn ſayeth: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayeth I know hym &amp; kepeth not his commaundements: ys a lyar, the truth ys not in hym. They be ſo haſty: forth now, they wyll not take this wyth them, that god may worke in them. He that ſayeth he abideth in chryſte owght to walke euen as he walke ſayethe .S. Iohn. Agayn where as ſaynt paule ſaieth we hold that a man is iuſtyfyed by fayht with oute the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ades of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law here be they perfyte but when ſaynt Paule ſayeth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh I had all the tonges though I could prophecy &amp; vnderſtand all ſecretes and al knowlege. Yea yf I had al fayth ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I cowld moue ſnowntaynes out of theyr Places
<pb facs="tcp:4364:48"/>yf I gaue all my goods to fede the poore, and though I gaue my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be burned, yet yf I haue no loue, I am nothynge ſayeth he.</p>
            <p>They make no reconynge of this. But what ys this loue? loue ſuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth long and ys courteous: Loue enuyeth not: doth not frowardly, ſwelleth not, dealeth not diſhoneſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, ſeaketh not her owne, &amp; ſo forth. Ioyne now Paules wordes and Iohns wordes together, for yf we boaſt of fayth, and yet contynew in ſynne, what fayth haue we?<note place="margin">Rom vi</note>
            </p>
            <p>Loke vnto whom ye geue ouer your ſelues as ſeruauntes to obey hys ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nts ye are whom ye obey ſayeth. S. Paule: whether it be of ſynne vnto death or of obedyence vnto ryghteouſnes. They heare S. Peter ſay thorow fayth god pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifieth owr hartes.<note place="margin">Act xv</note> But thei heare him not how ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly he deſyreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to leaue ther wicked liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, ſaiyng
<pb facs="tcp:4364:48"/>dearly beloued Ibeſech you as ſtrangers and pilgremes abſtaine from fleſhly luſtes which fyght a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule,<note place="margin">i Pet iii</note> and ſe that you haue an honeſt conuerſacion amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbeleuyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where as they backe byte you as euel doers they may ſe your good worckes and prayſe god in the day of vyſy tatyon.<note place="margin">ii. Pe. iii t</note> etc. for yf after we haue eſcaped the fylthynes of the worlde thorowe the knowlege of the lord and ſauior Ieſus chriſt) we be yet tangled a gayne therein and ouercome them is the later end wurſſe then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oh that theſe men wolde heare Moyſes ſpeke and be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the voyce of the lord ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi his prophets &amp; not take that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for ther purpos, &amp; run hedlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp in to the top of the hyll. For as many as be ſo haſty forth beyonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of the lord ſhalbe ſlayne of the enymyes, ouercom of ſynne, and
<pb facs="tcp:4364:49"/>drowned in ther owne luſtes, &amp; for lacke of true and faythful ſhepher des (which ſhulde exhort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dayly they ſhalbe ſo hardened in ther ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnes that afterward yf any fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man com vnto them they wyll not heare him, but rather call him Ipocrite becauſe he thretneth with the lawe, yet doth. S. Paul call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law owre ſcoimaſter which leadeth vs to chriſt for truly whoſe conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enre is not feared fyrſt with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe and ſo broute to repentaunce: ſhall neuere be meete to receaue a ſure hope of ſaluaryone by the goſple. Take hede therfore there be not in any of you an euel hart of vnbeleu to departe from the lyuynge god. And with ſaynt Poule alſo I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech you brethren by the mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye make your bodies A ſacryfyce, holye, and acceptable which is youre reaſonable ſeruyng of god. And faſhy on not youre ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb facs="tcp:4364:49"/>lyke vnto thys world but be renued etc. And with ſainte Paule alſo, I beſeche you Brethren y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiy<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercyfullnes of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you make youre bodyes a ſacrifice, holy, and acceptable which is your reſonable ſeruing of god: and faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not your ſelues, like vnto thys world: but be ye renued. etc. And let vs be admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed by the Story of thes rwelf meſſengers, to forſake oure owne wiſedome oure owne ſtrength, and our owne polecie, and inuencions: that we may wholy and altogether ſubdue our ſelues, and beobedient vnto the voice and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord onely: beleuig aſſuredli that he maketh rich, and alſo poore be maketk ſicke, &amp; health againe: he onely killeth &amp; reuiueth he only caſteth down and exalteth. He ſaueth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth, wherfore, Ido exhorte you, brethren beloued in the lorde Ieſus Chryſte again
<pb facs="tcp:4364:50"/>&amp; agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you chefeli y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te by the pitite in your conſcience to ſpye oute the lande of canaan for your brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whether it be by preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g readinge, writinge exhortinge or other wiſe Declaring vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the heauenly ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdom, through the Goſpel of the lord Ieſus. Yea the magiſtrates alſo, and all other officers, appointed by the king as well, as beinge commaunded by God: you alſo (by your fauour and pacience (do I exhorte to take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emple by the tenn vnfaithful meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſingers, which feread the multitud of ſtronge menne,) that yebrynge not an euel report vpon the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that through feare of men, we ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde miſtruſte the power of God: But rather prouoked by the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ieſua and Caleb, through a ſtronge faith, doo you acordynge to the comman<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dcemente of the lord And then are ye ſure, that the lorde
<pb facs="tcp:4364:50"/>wil appere in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tabernacle &amp; deliuer vs: Where, as elles we ſhalbe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerlaſting dampnation for our vnbelif But if we be feu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full Ioſues and Calebes, the ther is no doubt but our Moyſes wil ſo intreat hys father for vs, that theſe plages ſhal lyght onely vpn ſuche vnfaythfull meſſengers, thoro we whoſe euel reporte we haue byn ſo longe kepte from this heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, the kyngdom of god, &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe. Cheifly art they now to be admonyſhed that be ſo haſty forewarde, leſt they go beyonde the worde of the lorde, and in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true lyuely fayth Imagyn them a fayth after their owne mynde, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhal ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtyll to ſyn. But theirfore I ſay-where fayth is, it wurketh a knowledge of our great infirmytye &amp; weaknes, it wurketh alſo an inwarde ſorow of the hart, for this our ſynne and wyckednes,
<pb facs="tcp:4364:51"/>and it prouoketh vs i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this for ow! to pray vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, to cal erneſtly for ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually thorow chryſt to ouercome theſe re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with teares, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſure hope of victo tie, yf I haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded my neybour faith cauſeth me to ſatiſfe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent him becauſe Il oue him as my ſelf yf my neibour be vngodly &amp; by no meanes wylbe reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyled, yet fayth maketh me pray for him hartely, as I would he ſhuld for me yf I were i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke blindnes. He y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> fealeth not faith i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hy shart thys wyſe wur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng is blynd deceauech him ſelfe &amp; is ſtyl i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnbelefe tak hed therfor brethren that ther be not in any of you an euell hart of vnbelef to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the lyuynge god. And I beſeach the almighty god father of mercy and god of all comfort tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row our ſauyour &amp; redemer Ieſus Chryſte that he wyll ſo lyghten &amp; ſtrenghen them the hartes of oure
<pb facs="tcp:4364:51"/>rulers gouernours prophetes and preachers wyth his holi ſpret owr comforter: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hatyng all vice &amp; abomynacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſpecially couetouines) may neither feare men nor loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues but doo that onely which the lord commaundeth with a pure &amp; vndefiled conſcience. And that we for owr partes as true and louynge ſubiectes) may receyue yt at their handes without grudginge &amp; mur murynge, with lyke fayth and pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that withe a ſafe conſcience and glad hart, we may be alway ready at the commandemente of the lorde to enter the ſame lande of promyſe: whyche ys prepared from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, for all the true &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren.</p>
            <closer>Dominus, mihi Adiutor. et c. <signed>P N</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>IMPRENTED AT LONDON the Tenthe daye Of MAye: Anno dominice incarua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis MDXLViii.</p>
            <p>By william hill remaynyng at the Signe of the hill in Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Churche Yarde: and be there by him to be ſolde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4364:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
